I'm a contemporary artist and I show in art galleries and museums.
إنني فنانة معاصرة و اقدم عروض في صالات العرض الفنية و المتاحف
I show a number of photographs and films,
وأقوم بعرض عدد من الصور و الأفلام
but I also make television programs, books and some advertising,
و لكنني ايضا أعد برامج تليفزيونية و كتب و بعض الدعاية
all with the same concept.
و كلهم بنفس الفكرة.
And it's about our fixation with celebrity and celebrity culture,
و هي عن ولعنا بالمشاهير و ثقافاتهم
and the importance of the image:
و أهمية الصورة
celebrity is born of photography.
بدأت الشهرة من التصوير
I'm going to start with how I started with this concept seven years ago,
و لذلك سوف ابدأ بالطريقة التي بدأت بها هذة الفكرة منذ سبع سنوات
when Princess Diana died.
حين توفت الأميرة ديانا
There was a sort of a standstill in Britain
كان هناك نوع من الركود التام في بريطانيا ذلك اليوم
the moment of her death,
أو في لحظة وفاتها
and people decided to mourn her death in a sort of mass way.
و قرر الناس الحزن على وفاتها بطريقة جماهيرية
I was fascinated by this phenomenon,
وقد أذهلتني هذه الظاهرة
so I wondered:
و لذلك تساءلت
could one erase the image of Diana, actually quite crudely and physically?
هل من الممكن ان يقوم اي احد بمسح صورة ديانا بطريقة وحشية و حسية ؟
So, I got a gun and started to shoot at the image of Diana,
ولذلك أخذت مسدس و بدأت بالتصويب تجاه صورة ديانا
but I couldn't erase this from my memory
و لكنني لم استطع محو هذا من ذاكرتي
and certainly it was not being erased from the public psyche.
و بالتأكيد لم تمحى من ذاكرة الجماهير
Momentum was being built.
كانت هناك بالفعل العاطفة الكامنة داخل الجماهير لديانا
The press wrote about her death in rather, I felt, pornographic ways --
كتبت الصحافة عن وفاتها بصورة اعتبرها اباحية
like, "Which bit of artery left which bit of body?"
حيث كانت في الصميم كتمثيل جسدي
and "How did she die in the back of the car?" --
و عن انها ماتت في المقعد الخلفي لسيارة
and I was intrigued by this sort of mass voyeurism,
و فتنني هذا النوع من التدخل الجماعي في حياتها
so I made these rather gory images.
ولذلك صنعت تلك الصور الملطخة بالدماء
I then went on wondering whether I could actually replace her image,
و بعدها تساءلت اذا ما امكنني ان اغير صورتها
so I got a look-alike of Diana
وهكذا اتيت بصورة تشبه ديانا
and posed her in the right positions and angles
ووضعتها في الزوايا و الإتجاهات الصحيحة
and created something that was in, or existed in, the public imagination.
و صنعت شئ كان موجودا بالفعل في خيال الجماهير
So people were wondering: was she going to marry Dodi?
و لذلك تساءل الناس عما اذا كانت ستتزوج دودي؟؟
Was she in love with him?
هل كانت تحبه ؟؟
Was she pregnant? Did she want his baby?
هل كانت حامل ؟ هل ارادت ان تحتفظ بالطفل ؟
Was she pregnant when she died?
هل كانت حامل وقت وفاتها ؟
So I created this image of Diana, Dodi and their imaginary mixed-race child
و لذلك صنعت صورة لديانا و دودي و ابنهم المزعوم
and this image came out, which caused a huge public outcry at the time.
و تم نشر هذه الصورة مما تسبب في غضب عارم من الجمهور في ذلك الوقت.
I then went on to make more comments on the media and press imagery,
وبعد ذلك بدأت في التعليق على ما نشر الإعلام و الصحافة
so I started making reference to media imagery --
و هكذا بدأت في الاشارة الى ما نشره الإعلام
made it grainy, shot through doorways and so on and so forth --
وجعلته يبدو مبلور و أساسي و يعتبر طلقة عبر باب كل منزل
to titillate the public or the viewer further
وذلك لاثارة الجمهور اكثر
in terms of trying to make the viewer more aware of their own voyeurism.
و في كلمات تجعل الجمهور يعي اكثر متعته في معرفة الأخبار الخاصة للمشاهير
So, this is an image of Diana looking at Camilla kissing her husband,
فها هي صورة لديانا و هي تنظر لكاميلا و هي تقبل زوجها
and this was a sequence of images.
و كانت هذه امثلة للصور.
And this gets shown in art galleries like this, as a sequence.
و تعرض مثل هذه الصور في صالات العرض الفنية كمثال
And similarly with the Di-Dodian baby imagery --
و مثلها صور ديانا و دودي و طفلهم المزعوم.
this is another art gallery installation.
و هذا من احدى عروض الصالات الفنية.
I'm particularly interested in how you can't rely on your own perception.
انا مهتمة خاصة بانه كيف لا تستطيع ان تعتمد على فهمك.
This is Jane Smith and Jo Bloggs, for instance,
هذه جين سميث و جو بلوجز على سبيل المثال,
but you think it's Camilla and the Queen,
و لكنك تعتقد انهم كاميلا و الملكة.
and I'm fascinated how what you think is real isn't necessarily real.
وانني مبهورة بكيفية ان ما تظنه حقيقي ليس بالضرورة كذلك
And the camera can lie,
والكاميرا بأستطاعتها ان تكذب
and it makes it very, very easy
وتجعله سهل جدا, جدا
with the mass bombardment of imagery to tell untruths.
وبهذا القصف الشامل الذي تفعله الصور لقول ما هو غير الحقيقة
So, I continued to work on this project of how photography seduces us
لذلك استمريت في العمل علي هذا المشروع عن قدرة التصوير علي اغراءنا
and is more interesting to look at than the actual real subject matter.
وما هو اكثر تشويقا ان تنظر علي الواقع الحقيقي للموضوع
And at the same time, it removes us from the real subject matter,
وفي نفس الوقت, يبعدنا عن الموضوع الحقيقي
and this acts as a sort of titillating thing.
وهذا يعمل كنوع من الاثارة
So, the photograph becomes this teaser and incites desire and voyeurism;
اذا التصوير اصبح هذه المشكلة العويصة, الذي يحرض الرغبة
what you can't have, you want more.
ما لا تملكه, تريده اكثر
In the photograph, the real subject doesn't exist
اذا, في التصوير, الموضوع الحقيقي غير موجود
so it makes you want that person more.
وهذا ما يجعلك ترغب اكثر في هذا الشخص
And that is the way, I think, that celebrity magazines work now:
وهذه هي الطريقة, التي أظن ان مجلات المشاهير تعمل بها حاليا
the more pictures you see of these celebrities,
كلما ازدادت الصور التي تراها لهولاء المشاهير
the more you feel you know them,
كلما ازداد احساسك بأنك تعرفهم اكثر
but you don't know them
ولكن انت لا تعرفهم
and you want to know them further.
وتود ان تعرفهم أكثر
Of course, the Queen goes to her stud often to watch her horses ...
بالطبع الملكة تذهب عادة إلي الاسطبل الخاص بها لمشاهدة خيولها
watch her horses. (Laughter).
مشاهدة خيولها. (ضحك)
And then I was sort of making imagery.
وبعد ذلك كنت اقوم بعمل الصور
In England there's an expression: "you can't imagine the Queen on the loo."
يوجد تعبير في إنجلترا: " لا يمكنك تخيل الملكة وانت في المرحاض"
So I'm trying to penetrate that.
لذلك فإنني احاول اختراق ذلك
Well, here is the image.
إذا, هاهي الصورة
All this imagery was creating a lot of fuss
كل هذه الصور التي كانت تثير كثير من الجلبة
and I was cited as a disgusting artist. The press were writing about this,
وكان يشار إلي كفنانة مقززة. الصحافة كانت تكتب عن ذلك,
giving full pages about how terrible this was.
تعلمون, يعطون صفحات كاملة عن كيف كان ذلك بشع
Which I found very interesting that it was going full cycle:
والذي وجدته شيق للغاية في انه يسير في دائرة كاملة
I was making comments about the press
كنت اقوم بعمل تعليقات عن الصحافة,
and about how we know facts and information only by media --
وعن كيف اننا نعرف حقائق و معلومات فقط من خلال الإعلام
because we don't know the real people;
وذلك لاننا لا نعرف الاشخاص الحقيقيين
very few of us know the real people --
القليل فقط منا يعرف الاشخاص الحقيقيين
but it was going back into the press
ولكن كان يعود الي الصحافة,
and they were publicizing, effectively, my filthy work.
وكانوا يشهرون, بفعالية, عملي القذر
So, these are broadsheets, tabloids, debates were being had all about this work,
اذا هذه صحف الفضائح, الصحف الصفراء, المناقشات التي تجري وكلها عن هذا العمل
films were being banned before people had actually had the look at the work,
افلام كانت تحظر قبل ان يأخذ الناس فرصة مشاهدتها
politicians were getting involved --
السياسيون كانوا يتدخلون
all sorts of things -- great headlines.
كل انواع الاشياء, عناوين رئيسية عظيمة
Then suddenly, it started to get on front pages.
وفجأة بدأت تظهر علي الصحف الاولى
I was being asked and paid to do front covers.
كان يطلب مني ويدفع الي لأعمل الاغلفة الامامية
Suddenly I was becoming sort of acceptable,
فجأة بأت أصبح مقبولة نوعا ما,
which I found also fascinating.
والذي وجدته, كما تعلمون, مبهر ايضا
How one moment -- it was disgusting --
كيف في لحظة ما اصبح مقزز
journalists would lie to me to get a story or a photograph of me,
الصحفيون كانوا يكذبون علي ليتحصلو علي قصة او صورة لي,
saying my work was wonderful,
قائلين ان اعمالي رائعة,
and the next minute there were terrible headlines about me.
وفي الدقيقة التالية كانت هناك عناوين الرئيسية بشعة عني
But then this changed suddenly.
ولكن فجأة كل ذلك تغير
I then started to work for magazines and newspapers.
بعد ذلك بدأت اعمل للمجلات و الصحف
This was, for example, an image that went into Tatler.
هذا كان, علي سبيل المثال, صورة ذهبت الي تاتلر
This was another newspaper image.
وهذه كانت صورة لصحيفة أخري
It was an April fool actually, and to this day some people think it's real.
لقد كان ابريل مجنون حقا, والي يومنا هذا, بعض الناس يظنونه حقا
I was sitting next to someone at dinner the other day,
كنت جالسة الي جانب احدهم علي العشاء في اليوم التالي,
and they were saying there's this great image of the Queen
وكانوا يقولون انه هناك تلك الصورة العظيمة للملكة
sitting outside William Hill.
جالسة خارج ويليام هيل
They thought it was real.
لقد ظنوا ان ذلك حقيقي
I was exploring, at the time, the hyperbole of icons --
لذا كنت اتفحص, في الوقت, المغالاة في الرموز,
and Diana and Marilyn -- and the importance of celebrity in our lives.
وديانا و مارلين, واهمية المشاهير في حياتنا
How they wheedle their way into the collective psyche
كيف يتملقون حتي يصلون الي النفسية المجمعة
without us even knowing,
وبدون حتي معرفتنا,
and how that should happen.
وكيف يجب ان يحدث هذا
I explored with actually dressing up as the celebrities myself.
في الواقع لقد جربت ان ارتدي الملابس علي طريقة المشاهير
There's me as Diana --
هنالك انا في شكل ديانا
I look like the mass murderer Myra Hindley, I think, in this one. (Laughter).
أبدو في هذا كالقاتلة الجماعية ميرا هينلي, علي ما أظن (ضحك)
And me as the Queen.
وأنا كالملكة
I then continued on to make a whole body of work about Marilyn --
وبعد ذلك أستمريت في عمل مجموعة من الاعمال عن ماريلين,
the biggest icon of all --
الرمز الاكبر للكل
and trying to titillate by shooting through doorways and shutters and so on and so forth,
وأحاول ان ادغدغ عن طريق الاطلاق خلال المداخل و المصاريع وهكذا وهلما جرا
and only showing certain angles to create a reality that, obviously,
وعرض زوايا معينة لصنع حقيقة والتي, من الواضح,
is completely constructed.
انها شيدت بالكامل
This is the look-alike, so the crafting elements of this is completely enormous.
هذا هو وجه الشبه, اذا صياغة هذه العناصر ضخمة للغاية
She looks nothing like Marilyn,
هي لا تبدو ابدا مثل مارلين
but by the time we've made her up and put wigs and makeup on,
لكن وقت ما اقظناها ووضعنا لها الشعر المستعار و المكياج,
she looks exactly like Marilyn,
اصبحت تشبه مارلين تماما
to the extent that her husband couldn't recognize her --
لدرجة ان زوجها لم يتعرف عليها,
or recognize this look-alike -- in these photographs,
أو ان يلاحظ هذه الشبيهة, في هذه الصور,
which I find quite interesting.
وذلك ما اجد شيق للغاية
So, all this work is getting shown in art galleries.
اذا كل هذه الاعمال تعرض في معارض الفنون
Then I made a book.
بعد ذلك كتبت كتاب
I was also making a TV series for the BBC at the time.
وأيضا كنت اقوم بعمل حلقات تليفزيونية للبي بي سي في ذلك الوقت
Stills from the TV series went into this book.
لقطات من الحلقات التليفزيونية نقلت للكتاب
But there was a real legal problem because it looks real,
لكن كانت هناك مشكلة قانونية حقيقية لانه بدى حقيقيا
but how do you get over that?
لكن كيف تتغلب علي ذلك؟
Because obviously it's making a comment about our culture right now:
لأنه من الواضح ان ذلك يعطي تعليق عن ثقافتنا حاليا,
that we can't tell what's real.
اننا لا نستطيع ان نقول ما هو حقيقي
How do we know when we're looking at something whether it's real or not?
كيف نعرف, عندما ننظر لشيء ما, إذا ما كان حقيقي ام لا؟
So, from my point of view, it's important to publish it,
لذا من وجهة نظري, من المهم نشرها,
but at the same time it does cause a confusion --
لكن في الوقت ذاته فإنها تتسبب في نوع من الخلط--
intentional on my behalf,
متعمد من جانبي--
but problematic for any outlet that I'm working with.
لكن هو إشكالية لاي منفذ اتعامل معه
So a big disclaimer is put on everything that I do,
لذا هناك دائما تنصل شديد تجاه كل شيء أقوم به,
and I made narratives about all the European or Brit celebrities
وأعمل نوع من السرود عن كل المشاهير الاوروبيين او البريطانيين
and comments about our public figures.
وتعليقات عن كل شخصياتنا العامة
You know, what does Tony Blair get up to in private with his fashion guru?
أتعلمون, ماذا يفعل توني بلير عندما ينفرد بإخصائي الموضة الخاص به؟
And also dealing with the perceptions that are put about
ايضا في التعامل مع التصورات التي يغير اتجاهها
Bin Laden, Saddam Hussein, the links that were put about pre-Iraq war.
بن لادن, صدام حسين, الروابط التي تغير اتجاهها قبل حرب العراق
And what is going to happen to the monarchy?
وماذا سيحدث للملكية
Because obviously the British public,
لأنه من الواضح ان الشعب البريطاني,
I think, would prefer William to Charles on the throne.
في ظني, يفضل ويليام عن شارلز علي العرش
And it's that wish, or that desire, that I suppose I'm dealing with in my work.
وتلك الامنية, او الرغبة, التي اعتقد اني اتعامل معها في اعمالي
I'm not really interested in the celebrity themselves.
أنا في الواقع لست مهتمة بالمشاهير انفسهم
I'm interested in the perception of the celebrity.
أنا مهتمة بالتصور الخاص بالمشاهير
And with some look-alikes, they are so good
ومع بعض المتشابهات, هم جيدين للغاية
you don't know whether they're real or not.
أنت لا تعلم إذا كانوا حقيقيين ام لا
I did an advertising campaign for Schweppes, which is Coca-Cola,
لقد قمت بعمل حملة إعلانية لشويبس, وهي كوكا كولا,
and so that was very interesting in terms of the legalities.
وهذا كان شيقا للغاية من ناحية الجوانب القانونية
It's highly commercial.
إنه إعلاني للغاية
But it was a difficulty for me -- because this is my artwork;
لكنه كان يمثل صعوبة بالنسبة لي لان ذلك هو عملي الفني
should I do advertising? -- at the time.
هل يجب ان أعمل في المجال الإعلاني, في هذا الوقت؟
So I made sure the work was not compromised in any way
لذا فقد تحققت أن العمل لا يوجد به شبهة بأي شكل,
and that the integrity of the work remained the same.
وأن نزاهة العمل بقيت كما هي
But the meanings changed in the sense that with the logo on,
ولكن المعاني تغيرت, بحيث انه مع وجود الشعار,
you're closing all the lines of interpretation down to selling a product
فأنت بذلك تغلق كل سطور التفسير لبيع منتج--
and that's all you're doing.
وهذا كل ما تفعله
When you take the logo off, you're opening up the interpretations
وعندما تزيح الشعار, فإنك تفتح الباب للتفسيرات
and making the work inconclusive,
وتجعل العمل غير مقنع
opposed to conclusive when you are advertising.
علي غرار الاقناع, عندما تعلن
This image is quite interesting, actually,
هذه الصورة في غاية التشويق, في الحقيقة
because I think we made it three years ago.
لأنني أظن اننا فعلناها منذ 3 سنين,
And it's Camilla in her wedding dress, which, again,
وهي كاميلا في فستان زفافها, الذي, مرة أخري,
nearly got re-used now, recently prior to her wedding.
تقريبا أٌعيد إستخدامه حاليا, مؤخرا قبل زفافها
Tony Blair and Cherie. And again, the legalities -- we had to be very careful.
توني بلير و شيري. ومرة أخري, الجوانب القانونية--كان لابد أن نكون حذرين
It's obviously a very big commercial company, and so this little,
من الواضح انها شركة إعلانات عملاقة لذا فقد فعلنا ذلك قليلا
"Shh -- it's not really them,"
"شششش.....أتعلمون حقيقة لم يكونوا هم"
was put on the side of the imagery.
تم وضعها علي جانب الصورة
And Margaret Thatcher visiting Jeffery Archer in jail.
و مارجريت ثاتشر تزور جيفري ارشر في السجن
I then was asked by Selfridges to do a series of windows for them,
بعد ذلك طلبوني في سياف بريدجيز لاقوم بعمل سلسلة من الشبابيك
so I built a sauna bath in one of their windows and created little scenes --
لذا بنيت حمام ساونا في واحد من شبابيكهم, وخلقت مشاهد صغيرة--
live scenes with look-alikes inside the windows,
مشاهد حية مع متشابهات في الشبابيك,
and the windows were all steamed up.
والشبابيك كلها كانت رائعة
So, it's Tony Blair reading and practicing his speech;
إذا هاهو توني بلير يقرأ و يتدرب علي خطبته
I've got them doing yoga inside there with Carole Caplin;
انا وجدتهم يلغبون اليوجا في الداخل مع كارول كابلن,
Sven making out with Ulrika Jonsson, who he was having an affair with at that time.
سفين يغازل يوريكا جونسون, التي كان علي علاقة معها في ذلك الوقت
This was a huge success for them
كان هذا نجاح ساحق بالنسبة لهم
because the imagery got shown in the press the day after
لأن الصور عرضت في صحافة اليوم التالي
in every single newspaper, broadsheets and tabloids.
في كل الجرائد, صحف الفضائح, وصحف التابلويد
It was a bit of a road stopper, which was problematic
هذا كان نوعا ما نهاية للطريق, والذي سبب شاكلة
because the police kept on trying to clear away the crowds,
لأن البوليس ظل يحاول ان يفرق التجمعات
but huge fun -- it was great for me to do a performance.
لكن المتعة شديدة--كان من العظيم بالنسبة لي ان أعمل أداء
Also, people were taking photographs of this,
أيضا, الناس كانوا يأخذون صور لذلك,
so it was being texted around the world extremely quickly, all this imagery.
كان الخبر ينتشر حول العالم بسرعة شديدة عن طريق رسائل الموبايل, كل هذه الصور
And the press were interviewing, and I was signing my book. (Laughter).
والصحافة كانت تحاور, وانا كنت أقوم بالامضاء علي كتابي. (ضحك)
Further imagery. I'm making a new book now with Taschen
صور إضافية: أنا أقوم بعمل كتاب الان مع تاسكين,
that I'm working on really for a sort of global market --
الذي اعمل علي أن يكون من اجل السوق العالمية
my previous book was only for the U.K. market --
كتابي السابق كان فقط من أجل السوق البريطانية
that I suppose it could be called humorous.
لكني أفترض انه يمكن أن يطلق عليه ساخر
I suppose I come from a sort of non-humorous background
أنا أفترض أنني اًتي من خلفية غير ساخرة,
with serious intent,
أتعلمون, بنية جادة
and then suddenly my work is funny.
وفجأة أصبح عملي مرح
And I think it doesn't really matter that my work is considered humorous, in a way;
ولكني أظن أنه لايهم أني عملي يعد ساخر, بطريقة ما--
I think it's a way in for me to deal with the importance of imagery
أنا اظن أنها طريقة لي كي أتعامل مع أهمية الصور,
and how we read all our information through imagery.
وكيف اننا نقرأ كل معلوماتنا من خلال الصور
It's an extremely fast way of getting information.
إنها طريقة سريعة للحصول علي المعلومات
It's extremely difficult if it's constructed correctly,
إنه صعب للغاية لو أنه مبني بطريقة صحيحة,
and there are techniques of constructing iconic imagery.
وهناك تقنيات لبناء الصور الرمزية
This image, for example, is sort of spot-on
أنا أقصد هذه الصورة, علي سبيل المثال, هي نوعا ما دقيقة
because it exactly sums up what Elton may be doing in private,
لأنها بالفعل تجميع لما يفعله إلتون جون في خصوصيته
and also what might be happening with Saddam Hussein, and George Bush
وأيضا ما يمكن أن يحدث مع صدام حسين, وجورج بوش
reading the Koran upside-down.
وهو يقرأ القرأن بالمقلوب
For example, George Bush target practice --
علي سبيل المثال,هدف جورج بوش في التدريب,
shooting at Bin Laden and Michael Moore.
الإطلاق علي بن لادن و مايكل موور
And then you change the photograph he's shooting at,
وبعد ذلك تقوم بتغيير الصورة التي يطلق عليها,
and it suddenly becomes rather grim and maybe less accessible. (Laughter).
وتصبح فجأة قاتمة نوعا ما, ويمكن أن تصبح أصعب في التصويب. (ضحك)
Tony Blair being used as a mounting block,
توني بلير يستخدم ككتلة تصاعدية
and Rumsfeld and Bush laughing with some Abu Ghraib photos behind,
و رامسفيلد و بوش يضحكان مع بعض الصور من أبوغريب في الخلف,
and the seriousness, or the intellect, of Bush.
والجدية, أو النباهة لبوش
And also, commenting on the behind the scenes --
وأيضا تعليق علي ما هو خلف الكواليس,
well, as we know now -- what goes on in prisons.
إذا, كما نعلم الان, ماذا يحدث في السجون
And in fact, George Bush and Tony Blair
وفي الحقيقة توني بلير و جورج بوش
are having great fun during all of this.
يستمتعون للغاية و هم يفعلون ذلك
And really commenting, you know,
ويعلقون فعلا, تعلمون,
based on the perception we have of the celebrities.
بناء علي التصور الذي لدينا عن المشاهير,
What Jack Nicholson might be up to in his celebrity life,
ماذا يمكن أن يفعل جاك نيكولسون في حياة الشهرة التي يعيشها
and the fact that he tried to ... he had a bit of road rage
والحقيقة أنه حاول, وواجه بعض الصعوبات,
and golf-clubbed a driver the other day.
وإعتدى علي سائق في اليوم التالي
I mean, it's extremely difficult to find these look-alikes,
أنا أقصد, من الصعوبة أن تجد هذه التشابهات.
so I'm constantly going up to people in the street
لذا أنا أذهب للناس في الشوارع
and trying to ask people to come
وأحاول أن اطلب من الناس أن يأتوا
and be in one of my photographs or films.
وأن يكونوا في واحد من أفلامي أو صوري
And sometimes asking the real celebrity,
وبعض الأحيان أطلب المشاهير الحقيقيين,
mistaking them for someone who just looks like the real person,
أخلط بينهم وبين شخصا ما يشبه تماما الشخص الحقيقي,
which is highly embarrassing. (Laughter).
والذي يكون محرج للغاية. (ضحك)
I've also been working with The Guardian on a topical basis --
كنت أيضا أعمل مع الجارديان علي شكل موضوعات--
a page a week in their newspaper --
صفحة أسبوعية في جريدتهم--
which has been very interesting, working topically.
الذي كان شيق للغاية, أن أعمل موضوعيا
So, Jamie Oliver and school dinners;
إذا جيمي أوليفر وعشاء المدارس:
Bush and Blair having difficulty getting alongside Muslim culture;
بوش و بلير يجدون صعوبة أن يتفهموا الثقافة الإسلامية
the whole of the hunting issue,
كامل قضية الصيد,
and the royal family refusing to stop hunting;
والعائلة الملكية ترفض أن توقف الصيد
and the tsunami issues; and obviously Harry;
وقضايا تسونامي. ومن الواضح هاري.
Blair's views on Gordon Brown, which I find very interesting;
أراء بلير في جوردن براون, الذي أجده شيق للغاية
Condi and Bush.
كوندي و بوش
This image I've decided to show having a reservation about it.
هذه الصورة, أنا قررت أن أعرض, بعد التحفظ حيال ذلك
I made it a year ago. And just how meanings change,
قد فعلتها منذ سنة مضت--وكيف أن المعاني تتغير,
and there were a terrible thing that has happened,
وشيء فظيع قد حدث
but the fear is lurking around in our minds prior to that.
لكن الخوف يترصد في أذهاننا قبل ذلك
That's why this image was made one year ago,
ولذلك هذه الصورة قد أخذت منذ سنة مضت
and what it means today.
وما تعنيه اليوم
So, I'll leave you with these clips to have a look. (Music)
لذا سأترككم مه هذه الكليبات لتأخذوا نظرة عليها
Chris Anderson: Thank you.
كريس اندرسون,شكرا لك